<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The representation of the Committee of the Assembly for the north of Scotland, to the Privy-Council of that kingdom With some queries, by another hand, proposed to such Church-of-England-men as are advocates for the Scots Episcopalians.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28926</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834805</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199607</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264174572</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10127</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834805</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99834805e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199607)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:37, 1896:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The representation of the Committee of the Assembly for the north of Scotland, to the Privy-Council of that kingdom With some queries, by another hand, proposed to such Church-of-England-men as are advocates for the Scots Episcopalians.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>This item is bound following "The queries and protestation of the Scots Episcopal clergy" (Wing R1462) on UMI microfilm "Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 776.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Episcopal Church in Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199607:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199607:1"/>
            <p>THE Queries and Protestation OF THE <hi>Scots Episcopal Clergy</hi> AGAINST THE AUTHORITY OF THE Presbyterian General Assemblies and Committees, given in to the Committee of the General Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> June 29th, 1694.</p>
            <p>Together with the Committee's Answer and Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; with REFLECTIONS upon the QUERIES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Layman of the Church of</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 11.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:199607:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199607:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Cause of publishing the following Queries and Reflections upon them, is to obviate Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentations, and set things in their true Light, it having been the constant Practice of the Scots Prelatists and their Friends here, not only to put false Glosses upon things, but really to publish Ʋntruths, as Matter of Fact, ever since the Revolution, by which they impose upon those who are Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to Scots Affairs. The Truth of this cannot be denied by any who consider the Pamphlets which they have published from time to time against the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as by Law establish'd, both in relation to particular Ministers and Members, and the Acts and Proceedings of her General Assemblies and Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees: Nor is it unknown how some Persons of no mean Character did industriously misrepresent the Act for settling the Quiet and Peace of the Church, which was enacted in the last Session of Parliament at <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, June 12, 1693.</hi> before it appear'd in print, on purpose to render their Proceedings odious to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and the Opposition made to the sitting of the last General Assembly, who authorized the Committee here treated of, as also the Tricks which were endeavoured to be put upon them when they were call'd, are still fresh in the Memory of every one concern'd: So that these things, together with the Weight of the following Queries, not in themselves, but as being concerted by a General Meeting of the Episcopal Clergy in the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for themselves and their Adherents, will justify the publishing of them to the World; and that there may be a true Relation of the Matter of Fact on both sides, here is also an Account of the Committee's Answer and Proceedings.</p>
            <p>As to what concerns the <hi>Reflections,</hi> though the judicious and prudent Answer of the Committee, and the pertinent Protestation of Mr. <hi>Dunlop,</hi> are sufficient to satisfy those who are acquainted with our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and the legal and orderly Procedure of the Judicatories of our Church, yet something further was thought necessary to inform People here, amongst whom the Queries and Protestation of the Episcopal Party have made a Noise, whereas there was no notice taken of the Committee's Answer, nor the other Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; those who transmitted the Account of the one from <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to those who did send it in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick News and otherwise, through this Kingdom, having either suppress'd it out of Ignorance or Design. The Necessity of these Reflections, such as they are, will further appear to those who consider the Humour and Carriage of the Faction's Adherents in this place, being such as lay hold of every Opportunity to calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and by Consequence improve those Queries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as a special Occasion of begging and running about with their malicious Tattle amongst the Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Clergy, and others to whom they know such things to be acceptable: and therefore the Author of the following Reflections, out of pure Zeal for the Government of his Country, as at present establish'd both in Church and State, thought it incumbent on him to throw in his Mite; but does solemnly protest that he has neither Commission, Concurrence, nor Connivance from the Committee, nor any of their Number, nor indeed from any Minister or Ministers in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for what he has done herein, which he thinks fit to declare, to obviate the Misrepresentations of the opposite Party; and that no Mismanagement of his, though he be conscious of no other but Weakness, may be imputed to his own Party, whose Pardon he hopes that he may also obtain, though his meddling in their Affairs may seem officious, seeing he hath so ingenuously declared his Motive, and that he supporses his Reflections may keep the Adversaries in play for a while, till the Committee, or some deputed by them, shall be at leisure to take their Queries into Consideration, if they think that they deserve so much of their time.</p>
            <p>What's to be said further at present is, that all moderate Church-of <hi>England</hi>-men, into whose Hands this may fall, would do well to take notice, that those who pretend to be of their Party in <hi>Scotland, don't contend now for the Order of Bishops,</hi> it being apparent that they do, neither in the <hi>Formula</hi> which they offered to sign in <hi>1690,</hi> nor in the present Queries, make any mention of the Abolition of that Order, as a Cause of their declining Conformity to the Church of <hi>Scotland:</hi> Nor is their Renunciation of Episcopacy or Passive Obedience required, though we were obliged to renounce Presbytery, and the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness of defensive Arms, or else we could not conform to their Church-Establishment; for not only the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration
<pb facs="tcp:199607:3"/>of the solemn League and Covenant, but a Conformity to the Church, as owning the King's Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and the Government of the Church by Bishops, were expresly requir'd by Acts of Parliament, <hi>Sess. 2. Act 3,</hi> and <hi>5. Parl. 1. Car. 2. Sess. 3. Act 2.</hi> whereas in effect there's nothing required of them by the Act for Settling the Peace of the Church, <hi>June, 1693.</hi> but what they did seemingly concede by the <hi>Formula</hi> above-mentioned: And though they pretend to raise new Scruples now, as in their Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it will appear by the following Reflections, that they themselves did practise those things which they condemn in others. And whereas it may possibly be alledged, that they forbear making mention of the Abolition of Episcopacy, or requiring its Restitution as a Term of their Conformity, out of Deference to the Government, that cannot be the Reason; for those things which they impugn have also the Sanction of the Civil Government.</p>
            <p>But to conclude, those of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are likewise desired to consider, whether they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves would not be shy of admitting such as refuse either to own the Government or Doctrine of their Church; and therefore whether it be not very reasonable in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be wary how they admit those Men into her Judicatories, who not only refuse Submission to her Government and Doctrine, but by their Influence, those who adher'd to her were in the late Reigns exposed to <hi>Impoverishment, Banishment, Fining, Confining, Imprisonment, Torture,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> it self; it being no less than <hi>a Capital Crime, by their Laws, for any Presbyterian Minister to preach,</hi> Act <hi>8.</hi> Parl. <hi>1.</hi> Jac. <hi>7.</hi> and no Man <hi>could farm either House or Land without agreeing to a Clause in his Lease, obliging him and his Family to Conformity under exorbitant Penalties: And Landlords and Masters were to put away their Tenants and Servants without warning, if they went to Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> Act. <hi>24.</hi> Parl. <hi>1.</hi> Jac. <hi>7.</hi> and the Act in <hi>1681,</hi> when the D. of <hi>York</hi> was Commissioner. Now if these Laws and others which the present Parliament have declared to be <hi>impious,</hi> together with the <hi>Acts of Council</hi> which were yet more bloody and barbarous, <hi>as impowering the Souldiers to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and kill any Man they met, if they did not give satisfying Answers to their Questions,</hi> be duly considered, it's referred to the Judgment of any discreet Man, whether it would be prudent for the Presbyterian Ministers to take the Party who solicited those Laws into the Assemblies of their Church, without conforming to the Terms required by the Act of Parliament, <hi>June 12, 1693.</hi> viz. <hi>that they should take the Oath of Allegiance and Assurance, sign the Confession of Faith as their own, and promise to submit to, concur with, and never to endeavour the Subversion of the present Church-Government;</hi> which cannot appear to be harsh Terms to any Man who will seriously consider the <hi>Formula</hi> that the Party did offer to sign in <hi>1690.</hi> which, because it is often referred unto in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Reflections,</hi> and that it plainly demonstrates the Ʋnstedfastness and Shuffling of the Party, if compared with their present Queries, it's thought sit here to exhibit.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I <hi>A. B.</hi> do sincerely declare and promise, that I will submit to the Presbyterian Government of the Church, as it is now establish'd in this Kingdom by their Majesties K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> by Presbyteries, Provincial Synods, and General Assemblies; and that I will, as becomes a Minister of the Gospel, heartily concur with the said Government for suppressing of Sin and Wickedness, promoting Piety, and purging of the Church of all erroneous and scandalous Men. And I do further promise, that I will subscribe the Confession of Faith, and larger and shorter Catechism, now confirm'd by Act of Parliament, as containing the Doctrine of the Protestant Religion profess'd in this Kingdom.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now let the Querists answer, whether here be not a plain Offer to submit to the Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without any mention of the Objections insisted upon in their present Queries? whether they do not own here that there were scandalous and erroneous Ministers amongst them, which now they are so loth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess? whether they did not here acknowledg the Authority of the Presbyterians to purge out those Ministers, whereas now they protest against their having any such Power? whether they did not prevaricate with the Civil Government in offering those Terms, and yet refuse to conform according to the Act of <hi>June 12, 1693?</hi> and whether their offering to sign the Confession of Faith as the Doctrine of the Protestant Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed in the Kingdom, while they refused to sign the same as the Confession of their own Faith, was not a silly and gross piece of Dissimulation?</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199607:3"/>
            <head>Names of the DELEGATS commissionat by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meeting at <hi>Aberdeen</hi> upon the 5th Day of <hi>June</hi> 1694. for presenting the <hi>Queries, &amp;c.</hi> to the Committee at <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> are as follows:</head>
            <list>
               <item>MR. <hi>John Forbes</hi> Parson of <hi>Kincairden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Robertson</hi> Parson of <hi>Clatt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Lunan</hi> Parson of <hi>Davi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Patrick Harvy</hi> Parson of <hi>Forgon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Gellie</hi> Parson of <hi>Fordyce.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Barclay</hi> Minister at <hi>Peterhead.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Clark</hi> Minister at <hi>Methlick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Mill</hi> Minister at <hi>Ʋdnie.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Together with all the Ministers of the Presbytery of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> &amp;c. Of which Number of Delegats, these were present; and did give in the said Queries to the Committee foresaid, upon the 29th Day of <hi>June</hi> in the Year foresaid, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Robertson</hi> Parson of <hi>Clatt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Lunan</hi> Parson of <hi>Daviot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Clark</hi> Minister at <hi>Methlick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Mill</hi> Minister at <hi>Ʋdnie.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>And these of the Presbytery of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> viz.</head>
               <item>Mr. <hi>James Gordon</hi> Parson of <hi>Banchory-davinick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>George White</hi> Minister at <hi>Maryculter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Duntop</hi> Minister at <hi>Skeen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>George Smith</hi> Minister at <hi>Kinellar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Gilbert Ramsey</hi> Minister at <hi>Dyee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>George Seton</hi> Minister at <hi>Ʋppermachan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Metland</hi> Minister at <hi>Nigg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Crevey</hi> Minister at <hi>Newhills.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sic Subscribitur, <hi>M. Chrevey</hi> Clericus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>At the King's College-Kirk of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> of June <hi>1694.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe which Day <hi>being met the Ministers of the Diocess of</hi> Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen, <hi>together with Delegats from the Diocesses of</hi> Murray, Ross, Caithnes <hi>and</hi> Orknay, <hi>and from the Shyres of</hi> Mairns <hi>and</hi> Angus; <hi>for consulting anent the necessarie Affairs of the Church in this Juncture: And understanding that the Committee of the late Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterian Assemblie for the North, is to sit at</hi> Aberdeen <hi>once in this Month; Did therfore nominate and chuse the Brethren after-mentioned,</hi> viz. <hi>Mr.</hi> John Forbes <hi>Parson of</hi> Kincairden, <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Robertson <hi>Parson of</hi> Clatt, <hi>Mr.</hi> Alexander Lunan <hi>Parson of</hi> Daviot, <hi>Mr.</hi> Alexander Gellie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199607:4"/>
               <hi>Parson of</hi> Fordyce, <hi>Mr.</hi> Patrick Harvie <hi>Minister of</hi> Forgon, <hi>Mr.</hi> Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Barclay <hi>Minister at</hi> Peterhead, <hi>Mr.</hi> Alexander Clark <hi>Minister at</hi> Methlick, <hi>Mr.</hi> Alexander Mill <hi>Minister at</hi> Udnie: <hi>Together with all the Brethren of the Presbitrie of</hi> Aberdeen; <hi>together also with any others of other Presbitries or Diocesses who may be upon the Place for the time, or any three or one of them as their Commissioners and Representatives, With full Power, Warrand, and Commission to them to compear before the said Committee when ever it shall happen any of their Number to be cited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: And in their Name to present to them some Queries or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posals concerted by them at their said Meeting, relating to the Ecclesiastick Authority and Jurisdiction of the said Committee, and to demand Answers and Resolutions thereunto, and all other things to act and do relative to the Churches intrest,</hi> pro re nata. <hi>And to establish and constitut Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators one or more in their Name, To compear in their Absence, and to act before the said Committee as fullie and freelie as if all and every one of them were personallie present themselves. And appoynted one Extract of this Act to be given to the forsaids Commissioners, under the Clerk of the Meetings Hand, for their Warrand and Commission.</hi> Extracted furth of the Records of the Meeting above specifyed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Sic Subscribitur,</hi> M. Chrevey <hi>Clericus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Reflections <hi>on the Meeting of the Episcopal Clergy at</hi> Aberdeen.</head>
            <p>THE Gentlemen who composed this Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, having entertained the Committee of the General Assembly with Queries, will not I hope take it amiss to have a little of the same Entertainment themselves, and may certainly give a very agreeable Diversion to the Publick, if they will be pleased to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the following Queries, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what Authority they met? for by the Authority of their present Majesties they could not meet; and if by the Authority of the late King, whether or not their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was not Rebellion? If neither by the Authority of the late King, nor their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Majesties, how they came to act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their former Principles, <hi>viz.</hi> that all Convocations of the Lieges, without the King's Authority, is Rebellion? If they be Frastians in their Principle, according as their Party did swear, and profess them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be by the late Oath of Supremacy, and the 14 <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parl.</hi> 2. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. how came they to contradict this Principle by calling an Assembly of the Church without the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates Concurrence? If K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi> be <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d<hi>'s</hi> lawful Successors, to whom by virtue of the Supremacy and the Inherent Right of the Crown, the Ordering of the Government of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth properly belong, how comes it to pass that they meet in Opposition to the Committee of the Assembly which has their Majesties Authority to visit and purge the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not only meet in Opposition to them, but decline the Authority of them and their Constituents? If K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi> be not K. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d<hi>'s</hi> lawful Successors, how can the Querists appeal to them as the only Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199607:4"/>Judges in these Dominions? And see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they appeal to them as the only supreme Judges, why they don't acquiesce in their Judgment, which they have solemnly given by Act of Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> in lodging the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Jurisdiction of the National Church, by <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Sess.</hi> 2. of this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, on the Presbyterian Ministers, outed since 1661, and such as they have received or shall receive; and impowering them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Visitors to purge the Church, suspend and deprive? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And seeing the Committee which the Querists oppose have such a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whether they might not in Law deprive the said Querists for their Contumacy? And seeing they have not depriv'd them, whether they have not behav'd themselves with more Moderation towards the Querists, than their Party did toward the Presbyterians? And whether the Presbyterian Ministers were not beheaded, hang'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the late Reigns, for less Opposition to the Government? The Querists would oblige the Publick further to answer, whether or not their Meeting in this Manner, without the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Authority, if they still own his Title, be not a direct Breach of their Oath of Allegiance, wherein they were sworn to maintain his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction over all Persons, and in all Causes, against all Persons whatsoever? And if they own their present Majesties Authority, how they can acquit themselves of that Oath to King <hi>James,</hi> seeing they did also take the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, that it was not lawful to resist his Majesty, or any commissionated by him, on any Pretence whatsoever? And if they own that to have been a false Principle, why they did not declare so to the World, exhibit their Reasons, and avow their Repentance for swearing such a rash Oath? And further their Answer is desired, whether their assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling about Church-matters, in this manner, without the Consent of the Civil Magistrate, be not an express owning of the inherent and intrinsick Right of the Church; for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which their Party did persecute the Presbyterians to Death in the late Reigns? whether such a Meeting of such Persons who have not given those Proofs of their Loyalty to their Majesties that the Law requires, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when call'd on purpose to oppose a Committee cloth'd with their Majesty's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, be agreeable to the Principles of Passive Obedience, and not actual Resistance? and how that can be called the Assembly of a Church, which consists only of pretended Pastors, without Delegats from the People?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Some Proposals from the Ministers of the Diocess of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> for themselves, and in Name of the whole Episcopal Clergy within this Kingdom, who concur with them to the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of the late Presbyterian Assembly, now sitting at <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> upon the 29th of <hi>June,</hi> 1694.</head>
            <div n="1" type="proposal">
               <head>Query I. <hi>WHereas, according to the Principles of Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there ought be no higher Degree of Pastors in the Church than Presbyters, and all Presbyters are equal in Power and Authority, we desire to know by what Divine and Ecclesiastick Right these fifty or sixty sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Presbyterian Ministers, not being in actual Charge within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, did take upon them the Exercise of the whole Ecclesiastick Power of this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199607:5"/>National Church, and have exerced a more full and absolute Authority and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction over their Brethren, nine hundred or a thousand Ministers, who were in Office when Episcopacy was abolished, than ever the Bishops pretended to, who never claimed a Power to make Acts concerning the Church, without Consent of its Ministers.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reflections <hi>upon the First Query.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Design of this Query is, to charge the Committee of the Assembly with acting contrary to Presbyterian Principles, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercising a more absolute Authority over their Brethren, the Episcopal Ministers, than ever the Bishops pretended to.</p>
               <p>The Arguments on which they would found the first Part of the Charge are, because the Commission owns no higher Pastors in the Church than Presbyters, and that all those are equal in Power; and yet fifty or sixty surviving Presbyterian Ministers, not being in actual Charge within this Kingdom, did take upon them the Exercise of the whole Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastick Power.</p>
               <p>As to the first Part of the Argument, it seems altogether frivolous, and cannot infer the least Contrariety to Presbyterian Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that because they own no higher Pastors in the Church than Presbyters, therefore Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters should take upon them the Exercise of the whole Ecclesiastick Power: for it's natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to conclude, that seeing they own none higher, therefore they must needs think that the Ecclesiastick Power devolves on them.</p>
               <p>Nor is the second Argument any thing more concludent to prove the Committee's contradicting their own Principles, than as if one should argue thus, because all the Members of the House of Commons are of equal Power, therefore the Commons, or a Committee of their own Number, have no Power over a faulty Member or Members: or because the Members of the Assembly which met at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> had not in their single Capacities any Power over one another, as Apostle over Apostle, or Elder over Elder, therefore when gathered together as an As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, they had no Power, neither of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, nor by a Committee, to censure a faulty Member or Members.</p>
               <p>Then as to the third and strongest Part of the Argument, that fifty or sixty of the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Presbyterian Ministers, not being in actual Charge within this Kingdom, did take upon them the Charge of the whole Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astick Power:</p>
               <p>It may be answered, 1st. That the Case is falsly and maliciously stated; for those fifty or sixty surviving Ministers did not take upon themselves that Charge <hi>de novo,</hi> at the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of Prelacy, but were only restored to the free Exercise of that Charge, which by the Iniquity of the late Times, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical Persecution, they were unjustly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of, but had continued in the Possession and Practice of it, as Providence afforded them Opportunity, in private.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. That they did not take the Charge aforesaid upon themselves, but the free Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of the same was restored to them by the Parliament, in conjunction with such others as they should think fit to take in.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. That the Episcopalians, by denying them to have been in actual Charge at the Revolution, would have done well to have explain'd their Meaning: If by not being in actual Charge they intend their not being set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Parish-Churches, it may be granted without any Damage to their Cause: For by the Practice of the Prelatists themselves, a Man may be <hi>in officio,</hi> though not <hi>in beneficio;</hi> and if he be <hi>in officio,</hi> he may certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what belongs to his Office. And by their own Concession (<hi>Q.</hi> 2.) the Power of Discipline and Government is inseparable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199607:5"/>from the Power of Preaching; so that until it be proved that they were justly deprived of the Power of Preaching, they must still allow them to have been in actual Charge. And by Consequence this Part of their Argument falls to the Ground.</p>
               <p>Then as to that Part of it, that fifty or six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Presbyterian Ministers should exercise the whole Ecclesiastick Power of the National Church; besides what may be said to justify them from Theological Topicks, they have a very strong Argument from Politicks, by which the Prelatists ought to be satisfied, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own Concession in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation, as shall be evinc'd anon.</p>
               <p>For fifty or sixty Presbyterian Ministers may very well take upon them the Exercise of the whole Ecclesiastick Power of a Nation, when the Representatives of that Nation, in Parliament assembled, will own no other to have any Right thereunto: and for <hi>this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> as appears still by the Vote of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, <hi>that the Bishops and their Clergy were the great and insupportable Grievance of the Nation.</hi> And for this Cause, together with the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the illegal Method us'd in turning out the Presbyterian Ministers in 1660, and 1661. of which there were only those fifty or sixty alive at the Revolution, their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties, by Advice of their Parliament, after the settling of the Church-Government had hung above a Year in Suspence, did settle the same upon those fifty or sixty Presbyterian Ministers, and such as they should admit; so that according to the Appeal which the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latists have made in their Protestation to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as Supreme Judges under God in these Dominions, they ought to rest satisfied in their Determination by the Touch of the Scepter in Parliament, which is the only authoritative way by which they can determine Cases of that Consequence; though by this Appeal it would seem that our Prelatists are of another Mind. It's in vain for them to think of evading, by sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing that their Majesties were surpriz'd into that Assent, for they were sufficiently sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied how Matters stood; and all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that could be urg'd for the Episcopal Party, were represented and set off to the best Advantage, by the Viscount of <hi>T</hi>—, and others of their Champions, and back'd by the Interest of the high-flown Church-men here; so that if their Majesties had not been fully convinc'd of the Truth of what was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to them by their Grand Council, the Parliament, as to what Form of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was best for <hi>Scotland,</hi> it's not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable to think that ever they would have given their Royal Assent to that Act. So that if these Gentlemen had either any due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Dignity of Scots Parliaments, the impugning of whose Acts is no less than Treason; or if they had any real Deference to the Judgment of their Majesties, to whom they appeal, they would never be so bold, to say no worse, to appeal to them in a Matter which they have already determined in the most solemn and legal manner that can be, and much less to protest against the General Assembly of the Church or their Committee, as exercising Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction, tho not altogether by, yet with their Majesties Authority. And if the Party had but the least Remnant of Modesty, they would be asham'd to aver that the Presbyterians exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise a more full and absolute Authority and Jurisdiction over their Brethren, nine hundred or a thousand Ministers, who were in Office when Episcopacy was abolish'd, than ever the Bishops pretended to, who never claim'd a Power to make Acts concerning the Church, without Consent of its Ministers.</p>
               <p>It being very well known, that though the Bishops, to please the People, kept up a Form of Presbyteries and Synods, by whose Advice they pretended to make Acts; yet those Presbyteries and Synods were never al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed that Freedom and Liberty which they themselves desired, but were directly lorded over by the Bishops; of which the Scuffle which happened betwixt them and their Ciergy, about a Convocation in 1674. or thereabouts, as I take it, was a convincing Instance, for the poor Curates were forc'd at last to submit. Whereas it is evident that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199607:6"/>the Presbyterians do neither claim nor exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise any such absolute Jurisdiction over their Episcopal Brethren, the Assembly in 1690 having expresly declared <hi>that they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose no Incumbents simply for their Judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church-Government, nor yet urge Recordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon them.</hi> Nor can they give any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances that they have acted contrary to this Declaration, all of those that have hitherto been turn'd out being found really scandalous, or refusing to own their present Majesties; whereas the Presbyterians turn'd out in 1660, and 1661, could neither be accus'd as scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous in their Conversation, Heterodox in their Doctrine, or of refusing to own King <hi>Charles</hi> II. and yet the Prelatical Council turn'd them out meerly because they would not submit to the Bishops, by whose Influence afterwards it was enacted, <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Sess.</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. that all Petitions, Writing, Printing, Praying, Remonstrating or Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, shewing any Dislike of the Government of the Church by Bishops, was seditious. So that the World may judg of the Truth of those Mens Assertion, who say, that the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians do exercise a more full and absolute Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Jurisdiction over them, than ever the Bishops pretended to, who not only so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited the above-mentioned Act, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred with their Authority to establish it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Law. And seeing our Adversaries do own that the Bishops never made any Acts without the Consent of their Clergy, we would pray them to answer then, whether this does not plainly give the Lie to all their Pretensions of Moderation towards the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians in the late Reigns, which they mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified so much in some of their Pamphlets since the Revolution.</p>
               <p>They may, perhaps, object, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops did not do this in their Ecclesiastical Capacity, but as Members of Parliament. To which it may easily be replied, that they sit in Parliament as Bishops, which is their Ecclesiastical Capacity; but whether they did it in that Capacity or not, it's all one upon the matter; for, according to these Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Allegation, they did not concur to make such Acts relating to the Church, without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of their Clergy: and if they did it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Concurrence, then they lorded it over them and the Presbyterians both: so that they have brought themselves into a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma, let them get out of it which way they can.</p>
               <p>It may be further answered, as to their charging the Presbyterians with exercising a more absolute Jurisdiction over the Episcopal Ministers than the Bishops did, that without any Breach of Charity, if we consider the Practice and Designs of the Scots Bishops, it was neither their Interest nor Inclination to enquire into the Doctrine and Conversation of their Clergy; for Looseness of Practice and Errors in Doctrine, such as Arminianism, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were the Path-road to Popery and Slavery: for the advancing of which the Generality of our Scots Bishops did concur with the Court, as most, if not all of them who were in Office at the Revolution, do adhere to the late King still, and the Northern Parts of the Kingdom, where these refractory Clergy-men do now reside: as they are most opposite to this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment both in Church and State, so they did comply with the Courses of the late Reigns most of any. And whereas they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that the Bishops did not make any Acts concerning the Church, without the Consent of its Ministers; we answer, that if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded any Consent, it was only from those who own'd their Jurisdiction, and not from the Presbyterian Ministers: and they cannot deny but the Presbyterian Assemblies act with the Advice and Consent of all that own <hi>their</hi> Jurisdiction. So that the Episcopal Party condemn their own Practice by condemning us. All the Difference that can be alledged is, that those Episcopal Ministers who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain thus, are still in their Churches, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Presbyterians were thrown out; which is meerly the Fruits of the Government's Mildness, and does not one whit alter the Case, except they will alledg, which they never did hitherto, that none can be Ministers but such as are fix'd in particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And in truth this is but a very sorry Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199607:6"/>to the Presbyterians for their Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in suffering them to continue in the Churches, whence they could have as easily ejected them as they did vote them the great and insupportable Grievance of the Nation; that nothing will satisfy them, except they be admitted into the Judicatories of the Church, to embroil Affairs and overtun it afresh: And because they seem to lay such mighty Weight upon their being in Office when Episcopacy was abolish'd; they may remember that the Presbyterians were also in Office, in their sense, when Episcopacy was set up, without the Consent of the Ministers then in Office.</p>
               <p>Then as to that part of the Query, by what Divine or Ecclesiastical Right those fifty or sixty Ministers took upon them the Charge above-mentioned:</p>
               <p>It hath been answered already, that they never lost that Right, tho they were obstruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Exercise of it by Force; and as in general Defections, when the number of the Faithful is always the least, yet the Right is preserved in those few that continue faithful; so the case was here, the smallness of their Number is no Argument against the Justice of their Cause: For the Scriptures acquaint us, that the Witnesses for the Truth were reduced to two, (that is, a small, tho sufficient Number in Law to confirm the Truth) while the whole World wondered after the Beast; and we have often heard of <hi>unus Athanasius contra totum Orbem.</hi> The Waldenses were but few in Number compared with the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Idolaters, and yet the Succession of Church was preserved in them. The Arians of old, and the Papists of late did brag of their Multitude, but that was never allowed by the Orthodox as a concluding Argument. <hi>Chrysostom ad Pop. Antioch.</hi> hom. 26. says, <hi>Quid mihi cum multitudine malo unum pretiosum Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem quam obolos multos. Et</hi> hom. 40. <hi>Elias unus erat, sed totus Mundus non dignus erat qui repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deretur ei.</hi> Greg. Nazian. Orat. 25. contra Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos. <hi>Ʋbi sunt, inquit, qui Ecclesiam multitudine definiunt, &amp; parvum Gregem despicantur?</hi> This Comparison it's probable will be rejected as odious, and savouring too much of a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorious Spirit: but whoever will be at the Pains to consider, that the Divine Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Order of Presbyters is agreed on among all Christians in general, while that of any Superiour Order is granted by the most Learned of the Episcopal Party them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be meerly of Human Right; and then if we take a view of the solemn Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations which the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> lay under to have preserved the Protestant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Presbyterian Government in that Church, the undue Methods taken to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce Prelacy there, by the most notorious Perjury that ever was heard of under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; the Deluge of Profanity which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied that Change; the Laws for establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, which this present Parliament have voted to be impious, and the unhallowed Means and Instruments made use of to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and maintain the Scots Episcopacy: then if we consider the slackning of the Reins of all publick Discipline, together with the manifest decay of the Power of Godliness, and the Hatred which was evidenced against it by most of the Scots Bishops and their Clergy; when at the same time they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred with their utmost Power to bring the Nations under a Popish Government, to the manifest hazard of our Civil and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Liberties: and if to this we add the visible Inclination which that Party have still to the late King <hi>James,</hi> tho in League with the French King, and never to be restored but by the sworn Enemy of our Religion; the Doctrine of which they do apparently disown by refusing to sign the Confession of Faith: I say, that if all those things be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, it will appear with undeniable Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that our Scots Prelatists were and are engaged in a dreadful Defection, and join'd in Issue and Interest with <hi>Babylon,</hi> tho God by his Word and Providence did call aloud for his People to come out of her. Which Reflection being founded upon undeniable Matter of Fact, can offend no unprejudic'd Person, who will allow themselves time to consider of it; and therefore the Case being
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199607:7"/>thus, and the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> which was called by his present Majesty King <hi>William,</hi> whom God hath in a wonderful manner rais'd up to support and maintain the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Interest, which was ready to sink, having, as already hinted, voted the Scots Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and their Clergy, to be the great and insupportable Grievance of the Nation, let no Man tax me with being uncharitable, if I say that the Prelatical Party, having divested themselves of all pretences to Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction by their Defection, it must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily remain in those Presbyterian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters who continued faithful: and that this was the sense of the Body of Protestants in the Nation, appear'd by the unanimous Vote of their Representatives, who rejected the Bishops and their Clergy as an unsupportable Grievance; and by Law did establish the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction in those few Presbyterian Ministers, and such as they should admit: so that here's all that can be requisite to prove their Divine and Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astick Right to the Jurisdiction of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church. They had their Mission and Ordination as Ministers by the Hands of the Presbytery, which, <hi>in foro Ecclesiae,</hi> does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly constitute them Ambassadors of Jesus Christ, and the Nation by their Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives have submitted themselves to their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdidiction, as such: So that there is nothing wanting to clear their Right, either by Laws Divine or Human.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposal">
               <head>Query II. <hi>Since according to their own Principles, the Power of preaching the Gospel, and administring the Sacraments, and the Power of Discipline and Government are inseparable in the Office of a Pastor;</hi> Quaeritur, <hi>If that Constitution of Church-Government be lawful, which excludes the greatest part of the Pastors of the Church from having any share in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment thereof?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reflections <hi>on the Second Query.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Design of this Query is, first, to fix upon the Presbyterians an Inconsistency with their own Principles, in excluding the greatest part of the Ministers of that Church from any share in the Government, tho they own that the Power of Preaching, and the Power of Discipline are inseparable. And in the next place, to prove that the present Constitution of the Church-Government is unlawful upon that Account.</p>
               <p>As to the first: They may remember that it was the Practice of their own Church as well as of ours, to admit Probationers to preach without allowing them the Power of Discipline; whence it appears that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon us is not duly cautioned, nor can it infer any Inconsistency with our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. But what if we should answer their Question with another; Whether do they think that the Apostle, tho he was glad that Christ was preached out of Envy, would have admitted those envious Preachers into the Judicatories of the Church, to debate upon those Matters whereof they themselves were accused?</p>
               <p>But this Reflection of theirs will appear still more unreasonable, if we consider;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That tho the Presbyterians thought it fit to connive at their preaching, yet they never gave them any formal Allowance to preach; so that their denying them any share in the Discipline, seeing they never
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199607:7"/>had their Allowance to preach, cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any Contradiction in the Presbyterians to the Principle above-mentioned.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That it were highly imprudent, to say no worse, for the Assembly to admit those Men into a share of the Government of the Church, whom the Representatives of the Nation, who are the Body of that Church, did vote to be the insupportable Grievance of the Nation, which is a flagrant Scandal, whence the Party have never purged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and it will be allowed by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latists that Ministers under a Scandal, may be suspended <hi>ab Officio:</hi> so that they have no reason to complain when they are only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd from part of that which they pretend to be their Office, whereas they might have justly been excluded from the whole.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That for the Presbyterian Ministers to admit those Men into a share of the Church-Government, who during this time that they have been allowed to preach since the Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which is more than enough for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, have given no Evidences of their Amendment, nor Inclination to comply with the Terms of Conformity enjoin'd by the Act of Parliament: I say, for the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Ministers to admit those Men, were to betray the Trust which God and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have reposed in them, and to break down the Hedges and let in the Foxes to spoil the Vines: And if they should do so, how could they justify themselves, or answer the Reproaches which the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might upbraid them with; that when they had lodged the Government of the Church upon themselves, they let in their own Enemies and those of the State, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it?</p>
               <p>From all which it will appear, that it can reflect nothing of Unlawfulness upon the Constitution of the Church-Government, that the Presbyterians exclude those from any share in it, who, tho they look upon themselves as the Major Part of the Pastors, are accused by the People in Parliament as the insupportable Grievance of the Nation, who therefore deprived them of any share of the Church-Government, and left it to the Presbyterian Ministers, to take such of them in as they should think fit upon Probation, which gave the said Presbyterian Ministers a Civil Right: and as to the Divine Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Right, it was touched before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposal">
               <head>Query III. <hi>SEeing no Assembly of Church-Officers can justly claim any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or Jurisdiction over a Church, wherein that Church is not duly represented; and a Church cannot be represented in an Assembly in which their Delegats are not allowed to sit: And that by the Constitution of this Church, a General Assembly doth consist of Commissioners from all the Presbytries within the Kingdom.</hi> Quaeritur, <hi>How the late Presbyterian Assemblies can be owned for lawful General Assemblies of this Church, since they consisted intirely of the Presbyterian Party; and the Presbytries of this Diocess, and several others within this Kingdom had no Commissioners present at these Assemblies, nor had they a Call to send any?</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199607:8"/>
               <head type="sub">Reflections <hi>on the Third Query.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Design of this Query is, to impugn the Authority of the General Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, because they alledg that the Church was not duly represented in them, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting wholly of the Presbyterian Party, and wanting Delegates from the Diocess of <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen,</hi> and several others.</p>
               <p>These Gentlemen are not aware that the Objection may be retorted upon themselves with more advantage, and therefore they would do well to consider how they can justify the Authority of any of their Synods under the Bishops, to which none were admitted but those of their own Party; and in which the Body of the Church was never represented, there being no Elders to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the People: so that they had not the Concurrence of the Nation as we have in our Assemblies, where the People are not tyranniz'd over, but chearfully concur with what is done, according to that Pattern in the 15th of the <hi>Acts.</hi> And as to the wanting of Delegates from some Diocesses which are either refractory, or uncapable of sending, upon the account above-mentioned, it will no more prejudg the Right of the rest, than the Obstinacy of some Rebellious Counties can invalidate the Acts of Parliament of a whole Kingdom, to which they send no Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; for in all such cases the Right remains in the Majority of the sound Part: So that this Objection, however weighty it may have been esteem'd by our Adversaries, has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Solidity in it. And whereas they might insist upon their not having a Call to send any Delegates to the Assembly; it hath been answered already, that they were ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred uncapable of it by the general Accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kingdom by their Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; and it was never known in the World, that the Accused Party should be suffered to be Judges in their own Cause. But supposing that the Assembly should have called upon them to send in their Delegates, their Practice makes it plain that they would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd, their Authority, and embroil'd the poor Remainders of the Church which had escaped the Tyranny of the last Reigns, into vain and endless Janglings and Debates. Nor was it reasonable to think, that a Party who had solicited and promoted the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of those impious Laws against the Presbyterians, would ever concur to the Establishment of their Discipline, which they had laboured to destroy with so much Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: so that either for the Parliament, or the General Assembly to have called on the Episcopal Party to send Delegates to sit in their Ecclesiastical Judicatories for esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing the Government of the Church, had been just the same, as if they should have sent for all the known Jacobites in the Nation to have sat in Parliament for setling the Crown on King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> But our Querists may please to take notice further, That tho they assume to themselves and their Party, the specious Name of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors of the Church, the People to whom they pretended that Relation, did by their Representatives disown it, and accused them as an insupportable Grievance, and restored those to the Possession of the Jurisdiction who had the best Right, and upon whose Charges the Querists Party were Intruders, having neither sought nor obtain'd the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the People, or any Ecclesiastical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory; but entred upon the Churches of the Presbyterian Ministers, who were turn'd out without either Accusation, Citation, Conviction, Sentence, or a Hearing allowed them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposal">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199607:8"/>
               <head>Query IV. <hi>SInce by the Principles already mentioned, all Pastors have an equal Right to share in the Government of that Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are Members and Office-bearers: And since the whole Body of the Pastors of this Church, who were in Office at the time of the Abolishment of Episcopacy, cannot be charged with Ignorance, gross Error, Immorality of Life, or supine Negligence in their Office; We cannot understand how the Constitution of the present Church-Government, and late Assemblies, can be justified by the Presbyterian Ministers but upon this Supposition, that the whole Body of Pastors foresaid, are either no Ministers of the Gospel, or such corrupt ones upon the account of their Principles and Practice, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Church-Government, as that they are not worthy to be trusted with the Exercise of that Power which belongs to the Pastoral Office: which we cannot own without either renouncing our Ministrie, and declaring all the Acts of our Ministerial Function null and void.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reflections <hi>on the Fourth Query.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Design of this Query, is to vindicate the Body of the Episcopal Clergy from Ignorance, Gross Error, Immorality or Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in their Office; and to fix upon the Presbyterians that they cannot deny them a Share in the Church-Government, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they either look upon them as no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, or such corrupt ones upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Principles and Practices, in Relation to the Government of the Church, as that they are not worthy to be trusted with the Exercise of it: Which (say they) they cannot own without renouncing their Ministry, and declaring all their Ministerial Acts void and null.</p>
               <p>As to their Vindication, it comes unsea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably; for they ought to have put it into the Convention of States and Parliament when they voted the Bishops and their Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy the great and insupportable Grievance of the Nation: which seeing they did not do then, there was all the reason of the World to take it <hi>pro confesso;</hi> and seeing they are charged so heavily by the Representatives of the Nation, it were a piece of very great Injustice to suppose that August Assembly to be Liars or Calumniators, and not able to make good their Charge: and therefore until such time as they be purg'd by as good Authority as they are accus'd, they cannot charge the Presbyterian Ministers as being uncharitable for thinking them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of any Share in the Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; especially seeing they were so far from disproving the Charge, that they made it good to the View of the World: all their Bishops adhering to the late King, several of the Clergy joining in Arms against their present Majesties, above Two hundred of them being actually depriv'd by the Civil Government for refusing to own their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties. And the present Querists, by their Queries and Protestation, do manifestly strike at the Root of the Government both in Church and State; as shall be made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more fully afterwards.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:199607:9"/>
               <p>And whereas they alledg, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be charged with gross Error: It seems they have forgot that such of them as made Application to the Assembly, refused to sign the Confession of Faith, as containing sound Doctrine against Arminianism, Socinianism and Popery; by which they did virtually charge themselves with gross Errors; and their silly Proposal of offering to sign that Confession, as <hi>containing the Doctrine of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion professed in the Kingdom of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>but not as their own Doctrine,</hi> fixes the Suspicion of Error upon them with more force still: upon which account, their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties did with Advice and Consent of the Estates of Parliament, <hi>June</hi> 12th 1693, enact, <q>That no Minister or Preacher be admitted or continued unless he sign the said Confession as that of his own Faith, and the Doctrine that he will constantly adhere to.</q> So that it can scarcely be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd whether it be more impudent or ridiculous in those Querists, to blame the Presbyterian Ministers for not admitting them to the Exercise of the Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment contrary to the Laws, when it is not in their Power to do it: and it may justly be admir'd, with what Confidence those Men can desire to be admitted to the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of the Government of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when they refused to sign the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Faith which they own to contain the Doctrine of the Protestant Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as the Confession of their own Faith; especially when it's known that their Brethren of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no Ministers into their Church without testifying their Assent and Consent to the 39 Articles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then as to Immoralities which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they cannot be charg'd with: They would do well to remember, that not only many of their Number were guilty, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly accus'd of gross Immoralities, such as are hateful to be named, but their Bishops, who according to them, were the most es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential Part of their Church, were generally Men of ill Morals, and Arch-bishop <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> in particular is accus'd as such by Mr. <hi>Gordon</hi> one of the Querists, in his Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Reformed Bishop:</hi> And is it not very well known, that the two late Heads of their Church, from whence they deriv'd all their Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction, were grosly immoral, and their Church never so honest as to reprove them for it, in order to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them, or prevent the Corruption of Manners amongst the People who were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd by their bad Example, which makes their whole Body chargeable with the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Prophanity that abounds to this very day in the Nation? And they may be pleas'd to remember further, that besides those Sorts of Immoralities which are generally own'd to be such, they are chargeable with those of another nature; as the Breach of that Solemn League and Covenant which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them did personally sign, and were thereby obliged to resist Popery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and maintain the Privileges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and yet they avowedly broke through all those Ties by submitting to, and pleading for Prelacy, and preaching up the King's Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative over the Parliament and all Laws: so that by their Concurrence, the late King, when D. of <hi>York,</hi> though a Papist, sat in their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments as Commissioner, without qualify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself according to Law; and being by their Interest advanc'd to the Throne, took upon him, by his Proclamations, to cass and annul what Laws he pleas'd. Then, I suppose, they may also remember their taking of the self-contradictory Oath, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Test,</hi> in K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time, which the honestest of their Party refused: And all of them took the Declaration, that it was unlawful to resist the King, or any having his Commission. Notwithstanding of which, they offer to join with this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without giving the World any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Reasons why, or acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their former Error. Their shuffling with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by pretending to be mighty Zealots for her Discipline and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and yet offering in their Test or Declaration to submit to, and concur with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199607:9"/>the Presbyterian Government as at present establish'd in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so known. And now they shuffle with the Presbyterians again, and pretend they are not satisfied in their Consciences with their Government, though about two Years ago they declared by their <hi>Formula,</hi> that they could submit to it, and concur with it. Nor can they deny their Prevarication with their present Majesties, pretending that they would take the Oaths to be faithful to them, if the same were also impos'd upon the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; and they refus'd them notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Presbyterians being injoin'd by Law to take them. So that if the Querists had given themselves leave to remember those things, they might quickly have been satisfy'd, that the Presbyterians had ground enough to charge them with Immoralities; and because of their past and present Levity, to suspect their future Fidelity. For who can put any Confidence in a Party of Men, that have hitherto prov'd so unstedfast and false to all Interests that ever they engaged with?</p>
               <p>As for <hi>the Presbyterian Ministers looking upon the Episcopal Clergy to be either no Ministers of the Gospel, or such corrupt ones upon the account of their Principles and Practice in relation to Church-Government, as they are not worthy to be trusted with the Exercise of that Power which belongs to the Pastoral Office:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These Gentlemen may remember that they were not entrusted with the full Exercise of Discipline by their own Bishops; and Mr. <hi>Hickeringill,</hi> in his <hi>Ceremony-Monger,</hi> p. 124. says that he and his Brethren of the Church of <hi>England are suffered indeed to preach or to feed; but as to Church-Discipline, they are so many Ciphers; and the Bishops take from their Brethren the Presbyters, half the Work of a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter.</hi> So that the Querists reflect upon their own Bishops, and their Brethren of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as much, if not more, than upon us: for they withhold the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of Discipline from them, as thinking it no Part of their Office, though the Scots Bishops to please the People did allow their Clergy some more share; but the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians only withhold it as from Persons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a temporary Incapacity, till such time as they give Proof of their being worthy of it: and this is a farther Proof of what was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly asserted, that even the Episcopal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty themselves don't think the Power of Preaching and Discipline at all times unse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable; and yet we suppose, that both the English and Scots Bishops look'd upon their inferiour Clergy as Ministers, notwithstanding of their detaining the Power of Discipline from them.</p>
               <p>The Querists do also know very well, that the Presbyterians don't look upon a Prelate to be an Officer of Divine Institution; nor having the Power of Ordination either sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his own Person, or so as that Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot do it without him. And Mr. <hi>Hickeringill, Cerem. Monger,</hi> p. 108. though himself an actual Minister of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> calls the Prelatical Ordination a Schismatizing from Scripture, and all the Protestants of the World. And yet though the Presbyterians don't think this Manner of Ordination Scriptural; our Querists may see that they don't impose a Re-ordination upon them, nor declare their Ministerial Acts void and null: for the Assembly held in 1690, declared, as I said before, that they would <hi>not depose any Man for his Opinion in Church-Government, nor urge Re-ordination upon them.</hi> And though the Presbyterians are also of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that Episcopal Collation, and a Patron's Presentation, are not sufficient to entitle any Man to be Pastor of a particular Parish; yet they are far from treating the Episcopal Clergy as no Ministers: and yet the Querists would enviously insinuate so much, that they may render them odious to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> though if they should have treated them as no Ministers, it had been but <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> and upon much better Grounds than the Prelatical Party of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> both do treat them as such, by enjoining Re-ordination upon all Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters that have not been Episcopally or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, though at the same time they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199607:10"/>of Romish Priests without it; by which we have as much Reason as Mr. <hi>Hickeringhill,</hi> to say, that they schismatize from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and all Protestants of the World. And this does also make it evident, that the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians have good Ground to charge the Querists with corrupt Principles as to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, seeing their Bishops did all solicite and concur with the Act of Parliament in 1670. <q>Declaring all Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ministers since 1661, which hath not been by Bishops, null and invalid, and that they are no Ministers that are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise ordained.</q> And the whole Episcopal Clergy must, according to the Querists for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Position that their Bishops made no Acts relating to the Church without the Consent of their Presbyters, have given their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence with the Bishops to procure this Act: Therefore seeing the Presbyterian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters have but too good Ground to think that the Prelatists look upon them as no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, they had no reason to be sudden in admitting any of that Party into a share of the Church-Government.</p>
               <p>But as a farther Ground to suspect their corrupt Principles on that Head, they may remember, that when their Party was trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, they procured it to be enacted, <hi>Parl.</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <q>That by Virtue of the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy the ordering of the Government of the Church doth properly belong to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty and Successors, as an inherent Right of the Crown; and that he may enact and emit such Constitutions, Acts and Orders concerning Church-Administrations, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Meetings and Matters, as he in his Royal Wisdom shall think fit.</q> Now they know very well, that the Presbyterians look upon this as a very corrupt Principle; and accordingly this was annull'd by the Aboliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Supremacy in this Reign: and this Act being procured and submitted unto by all the Prelatists, they are justly chargeable with it as their Principle, though their present Practice is diametrically opposite; for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Principle they ought to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the present Constitution of the Church-Government, if they believed such a Power to be inherent in the Crown, and due to all King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Successors: For that the present Constitution is settled by their Majesties and the Parliament, cannot be denied; so that they have no way to avoid this Contradiction betwixt that Principle and their present Practice, but either to say, that they have chang'd their Principle on that Head, which apparently they have not; for in their Protestation they <hi>appeal to the King and Queen as Supreme Judg under God in these Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions;</hi> which being the Words of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish'd Act of Supremacy, gives us reason to think that they believe that Right to be in their Majesties still: or else, notwithstanding of all their Pretences, they must think that their Majesties are not <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's lawful Successors, and consequently to have no Right to that Power, which it's more than probable is the real, though not the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cause. And if they do still hold this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, it will be worth their while to consider how they could justify that trifling Opposition to King <hi>James</hi>'s Liberty of Conscience, which they valued themselves upon in some of their Pamphlets here since the Revolution: or, if they own their general and stupid Submission at that time, how came they to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves so mildly and quietly under the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations made then in Church-Affairs by a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Prince, when they are so very nice and scrupulous now to submit to Constitutions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by a Protestant Soveraign, for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Protestant Religion? whereas that Declaration of King <hi>James</hi> gave a very ample Liberty to the Papists, and yet they made no Protestation against it, as now against the Committee of the Assembly, and the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly it self, which act with their present Majesties Authority.</p>
               <p>Then having made it appear that the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians don't look upon them as no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, inasmuch as they don't urge Re-ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon them, the Querists have no Reason to think that their submitting to such Terms as the Law requires, though it may infer that they can comply with another Form of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199607:10"/>Government and Discipline than what they formerly own'd, that therefore it declares the Acts of their Ministerial Function null and void: Or supposing that they should hereby own that they were formerly corrupt in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and Practice as to Church-Government, it does not therefore follow that their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterial Acts are null and void; for they know that when those who have taken Orders in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are admitted by them, yet they don't declare all their former Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterial Acts null and void, though they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg their former corrupt Principles and Practices as to Church-Government, else they should rebaptize all such as are convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Popery, which they do not.</p>
               <p>Then as to their corrupt Practices in the Discipline of the Church, the Querists must needs be sensible of the Remisness of their whole Party, as to the putting of that in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise; whence it came to pass that Profanity is now arrived to such height, that it seems not remediable by any thing less than Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence. And though the Querists will not own it, yet we dare appeal to their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, whether they do not know it to be true, that the Generality of all those of their Party, who persecuted us with so much Fury, were openly wicked, and yet caressed by the governing Part of their Church, and look'd upon as its best Friends.</p>
               <p>And now that there has been occasion to touch their Persecution, the Querists may please to consider further, whether the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians have not reason to be shy of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting those Men into the Government of the Church, who by their Numbers may out-vote them, or their Unstedfastness betray them; and if the Throne should happen to be fill'd with such a Prince as some of those who were lately upon it, would join with them to overturn the present Government of the Church, under pretence that the Majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Pastors and People were for Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy: which, considering the Reason of State, given by the late Convention for abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing Prelacy, because contrary to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of the Generality of the People, would carry the same Appearance of Reason on the other side, to re-establish it; and in that case the Presbyterians would be under a Necessity either of defending their Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Sword, or submitting to such a horrid and inhumane Persecution as were those in the late Reigns.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposal">
               <head>Query V. Quaeritur, <hi>Whether the annual Office of Ruling (not Preaching) Elders, chosen out among the People, and joined with Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters in Kirk-Sessions, Presbyteries, Provincial and General Assemblies, and their Committees, to assist and concur with them in the Exercise of Discipline and Government, can be warrantably affirmed to be of Divine Institution? And if any Footstep of such an Office doth appear in the Practice of the antient Church; or any plain convincing Proof of its Institution can be produced out of the Scriptures: And if this Office be not of Divine Institution, whether a Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory consisting in part of such Officers pretending to Divine Institution, and to act by Warrant and Commission from Jesus Christ, be a lawful Judicatory?</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199607:11"/>
               <head type="sub">Reflections <hi>on the Fifth Query.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Design of this Query is to prove Presbyterian Government unlawful, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they admit of Ruling Elders in all the Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories of the Church,</hi> there being no Footstep of any such Officer to be found either in the Scripture or Antiquity, as they would insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate.</p>
               <p>We are glad to find this Principle granted by the Querists, that Judicatories, consisting in part of such Officers as do but pretend to Divine Institution, are therefore unlawful Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories. Their Brethren the Bishops of <hi>England,</hi> and the Courts kept under them, will scarcely perhaps give them Thanks for this Hypothesis, because Mr. <hi>Hickeringhill, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. Mong.</hi> p. 108. calls the <hi>Apparitors, Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Registers, Proctors, Canonists, Lay-Vicars, Vicar Generals, Commissaries, Officials, Surro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates,</hi> &amp;c. which are Officers in the English Ecclesiastical Judicatories, by some other Name than Officers of Divine Institution: And at the same time it justifies the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the Scots Presbyterians in the late Reigns, who could never see it proved, that the Scots Prelats were Officers of Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, though their Brains were almost beat out, because their Eye-sight was no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; insomuch that a small matter would have perswaded them that there was something more than a Poetical Fancy in the following Distich, composed by the learned and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious <hi>Andrew Marvel</hi> Esq; in his Loyal Scot,
<q>
                     <l>Instead of all the Plagues had Bishops come,</l>
                     <l>Without doubt <hi>Pharaoh</hi> bad sent <hi>Israel</hi> home.</l>
                  </q> which it's suppos'd the Author meant of Scots Bishops.</p>
               <p>But as to the Ruling Elders, if the Querists had given themselves the Trouble of reading Mr. <hi>Guthry</hi>'s little Tractate, what the <hi>London</hi> Ministers have writ concerning them in the <hi>Jus Divinum Regiminis Ecclesiastici,</hi> or what Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> writ lately on that Head, they would have found such Arguments for the Divine Institution of Ruling Elders, as were never yet answered: and seeing they have been in print, some of them for many Years, it had been worth our Querists while to have confuted them before they came to put this Query to the Committee, who they knew had neither Time nor Authority to enter into such Disputes.</p>
               <p>In the next place, the Querists would do well to answer these following Queries, <hi>viz.</hi> Where was this Objection, and all the other four, against the Lawfulness of the present Constitution of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when their Party did offer, by their <hi>Formula</hi> in 1690, to submit to and concur with the Presbyterian Government as it is at present establish'd in the Church of <hi>Scotland?</hi> How it came to be lawful for them to comply then and not now? and whether they did not know all those things as to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> then, that they object against it now? and if they did, as no doubt they must, why did they not put in such a Distinction in their <hi>Formula,</hi> as to the Government of the Church, as they did then concerning the Doctrine? and whether or not they have not some more hidden Scruples which they can bring out by Piece-meal, and dally with the Church and State till such time as they see whether the late King, with the Assistance of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. can re-establish the Scots Prelacy?</p>
               <p>But the Divine Institution of Ruling Elders being confidently impugn'd by the Querists, it's thought fit, lest they or their Party should triumph too much, to hint at a few Arguments to prove it, referring those who have a mind to be fully satisfied concerning it, to the three Books before-mentioned.</p>
               <p>But before we come to the Arguments, it may be necessary to describe what this Ruling Elder is, because that Officer is not so well known in this Kingdom as in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199607:11"/>
               <p>The Ruling Elder then is one chosen from amongst the People of more than ordinary Gifts and Piety, to assist the Pastor in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining those that come to the Lord's Table, in visiting the Sick, causing the Acts of Church-Judicatories to be put in execution, admonishing People privately of their Duty; and if they prove refractory, to bring the Matter before the Minister and the rest of the Elders: They are frequently to visit Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, instruct the Ignorant, exhort the Negligent, admonish the Slothful, rebuke those who walk disorderly, comfort the Afflicted, establish the Wavering, incourage those that do well; and, in short, to see Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Godliness promoted in Families: And for the more convenient Discharge of those Duties, every Elder has his particular quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Parish assign'd him; and they and the Minister meet once a Week, or oftner, <hi>pro re nata,</hi> to give an Account of their Charge. Then as to their Office in higher Judicatories, one of the most eminent in a Parish assists in the Presbytery and Provincial Synod; and a few from every Presbytery as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in the General Assembly. These are the Officers, and this their Office, which our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopal Querists think sufficient to render the Presbyterian Constitution unlawful, which is no very promising Evidence of their Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to the promoting of an Universal Piety and Reformation.</p>
               <p>But to come to the Divine Institution of these Officers:</p>
               <p>The first Argument is from <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8. <hi>Having then Gifts—Let us wait on our ministring, be that teacheth on teaching, he that exhorteth on Exhortation, he that giveth let him do it with Simplicity, he that RƲLETH with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, he that sheweth Mercy with Chearfulness.</hi> Where he that ruleth is distinguish'd from Doctor, Pastor and Deacon, and all of them are called the <hi>Gifts of God;</hi> which does ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily infer a Divine Institution of him that <hi>ruleth,</hi> as well as of him that <hi>teacheth</hi> and <hi>giveth.</hi> Nor is this the Sense of the Scots Presbyterians alone, but of <hi>Pareus, Piscator, Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> upon the place.</p>
               <p>The second is from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. — <hi>God hath set some in the Church, first Apostles, secondly Prophets, thirdly Teachers, afterwards Powers, then Gifts of Healing, Helps, GOVERNMENTS, kinds of Tongues.</hi> Here Governments are clearly said to be of Divine Institution, as a thing peculiar and distinct from other Church-Officers, who had also a Power of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Apostles, Prophets, Teachers; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Government was not all that belonged to their Office, as it was the whole of the Ruling Elders. And from the Nature and Necessity of Government it will appear that the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments here mentioned</hi> were not Temporary and Extraordinary, as that of <hi>Apostles, Tongues, Gifts of Healing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The third Argument is from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well, be counted worthy of double Honour, especially they that labour in the Word and Doctrine:</hi> Where a <hi>ruling Elder</hi> distinct from him that labours in the Word and Doctrine, is plainly held forth.</p>
               <p>It's true that there are Exceptions against the Arguments from these Texts, both by Episcopalians and Erastians; but they are sufficiently answered by the <hi>London</hi> Ministers in the <hi>Jus Divinum Regiminis,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lespie</hi> in his <hi>Aaron</hi>'s <hi>Rod,</hi> whither those that desire farther Satisfaction are referred; it being inconsistent with the designed Brevity to insert them here.</p>
               <p>Then as to that part of the Query, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any Footstep of these Officers in Antiquity? If the Querists please to read <hi>Ambrose</hi>'s Comment on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the 34th Chaper of his <hi>Apology. Basiliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Magnus</hi> on <hi>Isa.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Jerome</hi> on that same place, <hi>Augustin</hi>'s <hi>Epistle</hi> 137. <hi>Gregory contrae Celsum, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Aug. L.</hi> 3. <hi>contra Crescent. cap.</hi> 56. they will find that the Christian Church had them in the Primitive Times. And <hi>Ambrose,</hi> as cited by <hi>Calvin,</hi> on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. complains, <hi>that that Custom grew obsolete by the Sloth, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pride of the Teachers or Doctors, while they alone would seem to be eminent; than which a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Reason cannot be assigned, why these Officers were laid aside by our Scots Prelates,</hi> tho a shadow of them were still kept up in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199607:12"/>Parishes to please the People: which shows that the Querists do act <hi>mala fide</hi> when they reckon our Government unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for that which was practised in their own.</p>
               <p>Another of their Cavils against these Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers is, that they are Annual. But the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists would have found no room for this Objection, if they had considered what Mr. <hi>Guthry</hi> says, <hi>pag.</hi> 33. of his Treatise of Ruling Elders and Deacons, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>That Elders once lawfully called to the Office, and having Gifts from God meet to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise the same, unless they be removed therefrom because of Miscarriage, are still Elders: Tho haply in Congregations, where many qualified Men may be found, some may be permitted for a time to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease from the Exercise of the Charge, and others be put in their room, as was among the Levites under the Law in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Temple by Courses.</q> And to this we may add, that the Condition of most Congregations or Parishes being such, that they cannot allow a Maintenance for those Elders; and that many times Providence calls upon them to remove from one Parish to another, it's but highly reasonable that all those who are qualified in a Parish should bear this Office by turns, according as they are regularly called.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>The Epilogue to the Queries.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THese are some of the most weighty Scruples which we have in our Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences anent the Ecclesiastical Authority of the Committee deputed from the late Presbyterian Assembly, and these we propose not out of any fear of being tried in relation to our Life and Doctrine; in which we are willing to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our selves to an impartial Trial by any competent Judicatory Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastick within this Kingdom: Nor, as if we would not have a due Regard to this Committee, if they clothed themselves with a Delegation from the Civil Power: But that we cannot (until we be resolved in these Scruples) without betraying the Liberties of this National Church, acknowledg any Ecclesiastick Power or Jurisdiction in this Committee, or their Constituents, to be Judges of any of our Number.</hi> And therefore, <hi>We hope the Members of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee will either desist from any farther Procedor against us, or else give us a satisfactory Answer to these Proposals, which we have good ground to expect from them; since it is both just and reasonable in it self, and well-becoming the Character they own of Gospel-Ministers, that they should satisfy the Consciences of the scrupulous concerning their Authority and Jurisdiction before they urge them to submit thereunto: And that in regard the Assembly in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions to the Commission, have required the same to take all due Pains to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199607:12"/>inform, convince and satisfy such as think that they have receded from their known Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These Queries were concerted by the General Meeting at Old <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Sic subscribitur,</hi> M. Chrevey, <hi>Clericus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Reflections <hi>on the Epilogue to the Queries.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHether these Scruples be weighty or not, and whether most of them do not as much condemn the Practices of their own Church as that of the Presbyterians, let those who impartially peruse the foregoing Reflections be Judges. And whether the Presbyterians have not reason to think that Error in Doctrine, and Scandal in Practice have not a considerable Influence in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining a Trial, let what hath been charged on the whole Party from undeniable Matter of Fact determine: Or, whether the Committee was not a competent Judicatory, both as to Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Ecclesiastical Right, when the General Assembly of the Church, from whom they had their Authority, are own'd by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives of all the Protestants in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, assembled in a Parliamentary way, to have the only Right of Ecclesiastical Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, let law and Divinity decide. And consequently whether it be just and reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think that their submitting to the Committee, or their Constituents, would have been a betraying of the Liberties of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church, when the General Assembly are in full Parliament nationally clothed with a National Right; and the far greatest part of the Nation do calmly acquiesce and testify their Concurrence, by sending their Delegates, the ruling Elders, from the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Quarters of the Nation to sit in the Assembly.</p>
            <p>The Querists would also do well to consider with what Confidence they and their Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuents can take upon them the Name of the National Church, when the Bishops from whom they had their Pastoral Authority are vomited out by the Convention, as the great and insupportable Grievance of the Nation: When in their General Meeting, as they call it, at old <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> they had no Delegates to represent the People, or testify their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent; and when the greatest part of the People, in most parts of the Nation, at least of those who by Gospel-Rules are capable of being admitted to enjoy all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in the Church, have both by their Representatives in Parliament, and their own Practice throughout the Kingdom, testified their general dislike of the Bishops and their Clergy. And let them answer whether this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating to themselves the Government of the Church without the Churches Consent, be not a lording it over God's Heritage; of which Name they have injuriously bereft the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and appropriated the same to themselves under the Greek Title of Clergy, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not without a special Providence, that their Prelacy might be clearly evinc'd to be that prohibited Lording it over God's Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, seeing they alone, <hi>si Diis placet,</hi> will needs be call'd so; and that their Prelates lorded it over them, is beyond Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>Their pretended Deference to the Civil Power will fall properly under the Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon their Protestation. But here it's fit to take notice of the Weakness of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons from which they pretended to hope that the Committee should either give a satisfactory Answer to their Queries, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist from proceeding against them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:199607:13"/> 1. Because according to them they had no Ecclesiastical Authority, tho all their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections against it were either mistaken Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact, or such as did more strongly militate against that Ecclesiastical Authority which they themselves did practise and own; and if there be any of their Objections which don't fall under those two Heads, they were answered in Print many Years ago. So that the Committee, tho they had both had Time and Commission to dispute with them, might very well have refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them thither, or demanded Replies to those Answers before they had given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves any farther Trouble. Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the Querists had rather a design to cavil and gain time, than any desire to be satisfied in their Consciences. But fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if Cavils and Exceptions to Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Judicatories ought to suspend their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure, then Hereticks and Schismaticks should never want an invincible Argument.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because they own the Character of Gospel-Ministers, which would seem to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that tho they own it, yet they don't deserve it; and this cannot be understood as a wresting of their Sense, if we consider their former Act of Parliament, declaring all those who were not Episcopally ordained, to be no Ministers. And in this Case let any Man judg whether the Committee had any reason to stop their Procedure against them. But further, the Querists would do well to consider, whether it be any way contrary to the Character of Gospel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters to proceed to Censure against Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, because they are contentious, and will insist either upon Falsities, or Objections answered over and over. And I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded that to any unbiassed Man these Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries will appear to proceed more from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention than Scruple, if they consider that the weightiest of them were answered long ago, that others of them did directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their own Practice, and that the Party have several times since the Revolution, offered Submission to the Government of the Church without mentioning any of them: and therefore, seeing there is very great Ground to think that these Queries had their Rise from Contention, the Apostle's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer is plain, <hi>But if any Man be contentions, we have no such Custom, neither the Churches of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Because of the Assembly's Instructions, for which peruse the Committee's Answer in the Negative.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Committee's Answer to the Queries.</head>
            <p>
               <q>THE Committee finding that the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions proposed do strike at the Root of Presbyterian Government, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Establishment thereof according to the Laws of this Kingdom, and do overturn the Authority of this Committee, with which they are entrusted by the Assembly, Do judg it not becoming and sutable to the Trust reposed in this Judicatory, to enter in Debate with any particular Persons few or moe about the Constitution and Power of the present established Government of this Church. <hi>And,</hi> Do think that if it had indeed been Satisfaction to their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences which they desired, they both might have long before this time, and yet may take more proper and obvious Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures for that end. Besides that, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee have other urging and important Work committed by the General Assembly to them, which cannot allow them so much Time for Debates and Disputes, as the Matter proposed would require, nor have they any Commission for that Effect.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199607:13"/>
            <head>Protestation and Appeal given in at <hi>Aberdeen</hi> upon the 29th Day of <hi>June</hi> 1694, under form of Instrument, to the Committee of the late Presbyterian Assembly, by the Ministers Delegat for that end from the Diocess of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> for themselves, and in the Name of all their Adherents.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WE the Ministers of the Diocesses of</hi> Aberdeen, Murray, Rosse, Caithness, Orkney, <hi>and of the Shyres of</hi> Angus <hi>and</hi> Mairns, <hi>Do hereby declare that we cannot own the Assemblies of our Presbyterian Brethren since the last Establishment of their Government, to have been the full and lawful Representatives of this National Church; and consequentlie no Person or Persons whatsomever by virtue of any Delegation from them, can justlie claim a Power to be the Judges of our Lives and Doctrine, according to what we have expressed in the Queries given in to this Committee, the Tenor whereof is</hi> ut supra.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the which Queries we have received no satisfactory Answer; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that they have manifestly stated themselves as Parties against these of our Character and Perswasion;</hi> Therefore <hi>for maintaining the Liberties of this National Church, and for many other Reasons moving us thereto, which we are resolved in due time to publish to the World, we find our selves obliged unanimously to testify against the pretended Ecclesiastick Authority of this Committee, and to protest against all their Proceedings, Acts and Sentences in the Quality of an Ecclesiastick Judicatorie, and to appeal to their Majesties K.</hi> William <hi>and Q.</hi> Mary, <hi>as Supreme Judges under God within these Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and to the next lawfullie constitute and orderlie called General Assemblie of this National Church. And we do hereby protest against any Sentence past or to be past against any of our Number that are cited or may be cited before this Committee, and do appeal to their Majesties as said is: And this we do not as if we would protect any that are trulie guiltie, (if any such be amongst us) nor as if we would not give all due Deference to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, in submitting to them, if they clothed themselves only with a Delegation from the Civil Power: But that we cannot (until we be resolved in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Scruples) acknowledg any Ecclesiastical Power or Jurisdiction in this Committee, or their Constituents, to be Judges of any of our Number. And finally, we protest that this our Protestation and Appeal, together with the Queries above-mentioned, as they were given in before entring this Protestation, be inserted</hi> verbatim <hi>in the Records of this Committee,</hi> ad futuram rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiam. <hi>Sic subscribitur.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199607:14"/>
            <head>Reflections <hi>on the Protestation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Protestation referring to the Queries above-mentioned for the Reasons of it, it follows naturally that the Reader should be referred to the Reflections upon those Queries, where he will find their Reasons confidered. So that all that remains now to be done is, to consider the Deference which the Querists pretend to the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and any other Reason which may perhaps have escap'd them in their Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>Whatever regard they may pretend to the Civil Government, it's plain that they do manifestly impugn its Authority in a very sawcy and undecent manner, by denying the Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction of the General Assemblies since the Revolution, tho the same be established in them by the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as far as Human Law can do it; and yet the Querists have not so much as one honourable Expression of Deference to the Sanction of the Civil Government confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Divine and Ecclesiastical Right, which is so much the more remarkable, and the greater Proof of Disrespect to the Civil Government in them, because, as was hinted before, the whole Party in the late Reigns did, by Act of Parliament, lodg such a Power in the King's own Person, <hi>that he might by virtue of the Supremacy, and an inherent Right of the Crown, order the Government of the Church, enact and emit such Constitutions, Acts and Orders con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church-Administrations, Persons, Meetings and Matters, as he in his Royal Wisdom shall think sit.</hi> Now if the Party had believed that the Government of the Church was of Divine Institution, they durst never have allowed the King such an ample Power concerning it, nor have submitted to it: And if they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the King has really such a Power as is here expressed, how comes it that they do not submit to the Church-Government, as it is now establish'd by their present Majesties and the Parliament? And seeing they do in such an obstinate manner protest against the Authority of the General Assemblies, who, besides their Ecclesiastical and Divine Right to the Jurisdiction over the National Church, have all the Civil Right which the King and Parliament can give, it must necessarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that either they think King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> have not so good a Right to order the Government of the Church, as the late Kings had; that his Right is diminish'd by the Concurrence of the Parliament; or that the Assemblies pretending to a Divine Right, together with the Civil Right, makes it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for them to submit. The two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer they will not own, tho there's reason to think the main Objection lies there; but they are asham'd, or at least shy to own it openly, because that would render them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the Government's Protection, and make the People cry out, Shame upon them, that they should have by Act of Parliament allowed more Power to <hi>Profane</hi> and <hi>Popish Princes</hi> in Church-Matters, than they will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Protestant Princes:</hi> and therefore we will suppose that the main Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is, because the Assembly do also plead a Divine Right, which they must deny, either because they want Bishops; and if so, they do both deny a Power of Jurisdiction to most if not all of the Reformed Churches in <hi>Europe;</hi> for none of them have such Bishops as theirs were even as to Matters of Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and also condemn themselves for offering to submit to and concur with that Government as they did in 1690. and if they scruple their Authority because they had not Delegates from all the Prelatical Clergy of <hi>Scotland,</hi> it has been answered already.</p>
            <p>But to be plain with them, if their former Principle of the King's having such a Power by virtue of the Supremacy, and as an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the Crown, be true, then they ought
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199607:14"/>to obey their present Majesties, who have set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Presbyterian-Government in <hi>Scotland</hi> as most agreeable to the Word of God; for so they have enacted it: or if that former Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of theirs was false, then in Conscience they ought to publish to the World that they declare it so; and in that Case they must allow that the Presbyterian Ministers had reason to be shy in admitting them into a Share of the Church-Government, because of their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Principles and Practices concerning it.</p>
            <p>But if they think that the King alone has that Power, and that they cannot submit to the present Acts concerning the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are enacted by and with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Parliament, then it shows plainly how little Deference they have to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment who would set the two constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Parts in opposition to one another: for that the Government of <hi>Scotland</hi> is by King and Parliament, and no other, there's no Man able to deny; though the Prelatical Party did their utmost Endeavour to overturn it in the two late Reigns, and throw us into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomless Gulph of an Absolute Monarchy, by giving the King such Power both in Civil and Ecclesiastical Affairs, that Parliaments would have been thereby quite destroy'd. The Power they gave the Kings in Church-Affairs, we have just now heard; and for that in Civil-Affairs, we refer to the 18th Act of the Parliament held by the D. of <hi>York;</hi> wherein it was enacted, that all Jurisdiction doth so reside in his Majesty, that he may by himself, or any commissionated by him, take Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, and give Decision of any Cases or Causes he pleases.</p>
            <p>Now by their Appealing to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties without any mention of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by whose Advice and Consent the Laws against the Matter of their Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were enacted; it's plain that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, by a seeming Excess of Zeal for the Prerogative, to break the very Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Constitution of our Government: as if their Majesties, according to the former Doctrine and Politicks of their Party, could of themselves revoke those Laws, or totally dispense with the Execution of them, without the Authority of the Parliament. And yet at the same time they are so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, as to accuse their Majesties of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing call'd an irregular and ill-constituted Assembly, and to protest against all the Acts and Proceedings of the late Assembly, and their Committee, which acted as Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical Judicatories by their Majesties Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; who in the <hi>Act of Parliament settling Presbyterian Government, have expresly authoriz'd the Presbyterian Ministers to appoint Visitors, and purge out scandalous and insufficient Ministers, and to suspend and deprive such as are contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and proven guilty:</hi> By which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee might legally deprive all the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists, and they in Conscience should be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to submit, as having referr'd the Case to their Majesties as supreme Judges under God, seeing they have g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thus in that very Act, as also, <q>That Presbyterian Government is most agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Word of God, most conducive to the Advancement of true Piety and Godliness, and establishing the Peace of the Realm.</q> And by another Act of that same Parliament, have abolish'd the Supremacy, and left the Church in power to hold her own Assemblies as Ecclesiastical Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. So that here's the Judgment of their Majesties, to whom our Querists have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd, fully against them. And if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the Authority of the Assembly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they do not only act by their Majesties Authority, but claim a Privilege of acting of themselves by Divine Right, then they plainly declare themselves Erastians, and not only condemn us, but the Church of <hi>England;</hi> whose Prolocutor, in her last Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, did argue against making any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in her Constitution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> alledging that it was Apostolical: and if our Querists be Erastians in their Principles, they do still contradict their Principles by their Practice, in not submitting to that Church-Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is settled by the Magistrates Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. So that in plain terms, our Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonists seem wholly to be influenc'd by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and Interest, and have nothing of Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastness either in Principle or Practice.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199607:15"/>
            <p> One of the Reasons given by the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists for their Protestation is, because the Presbyterian Ministers have manifestly stated themselves as Parties against those of their Character and Perswasion, which is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest Untruth; for the Assembly in 1690, declared, as hath been already said, that they would <hi>depose no Incumbents simply for their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning Church-Government, nor yet urge Re-ordination upon them:</hi> and it is very well known, that not one hath been hitherto turn'd out by any Judicatory Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastick, but either upon the account of their Disaffection to the Civil Government, or scandalous Life. So that this Pretence is a meer Subterfuge, and maliciously in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted upon to render the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> odious to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that so those of that Party might have more plausible Pretexts to solicite his Majesty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Scots Presbyterians. But suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing that it were true, this Objection of theirs will militate as much against them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves as against us, and more; for we could on much better Ground except against their sitting as Judges upon us, because they did plainly state themselves as Parties, and would oblige us to an express Renunciation of our Principles; whereas there is no such thing requir'd of them. But however, if such Objections be allowed, then the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of Hereticks shall escape; for they can truly say, that the Orthodox do manifestly state themselves as Parties against those of their Character and Perswasion, and yet this does not incapacitate them from being Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, no more than those who declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves for K. <hi>William,</hi> are uncapable of judging those who are accus'd of treasonable Designs to bring in the late K. <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of all things this is the most surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, that the Querists should have the Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to appeal to their Majesties against themselves; for it's plain that the Assembly, whom they decline as Judges, are constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted such by their Majesties Authority, and by and with the Advice and Consent of that Parliament which settled the Crown on their Majesties Head: whence it's apparent, that they strike at the very Foundation of the Civil Government, and not only charge their Majesties with a gross Piece of Male-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration in calling a disorderly and ill-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted Assembly to tyrannize over the Clergy, but disown the Authority of King and Parliament in the most audacious and insolent Manner that can be, by their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modest and seditious Protestation, which in the late Reigns would have cost them their Liberties if not their Lives; for Mr. <hi>James Guthry</hi> was beheaded because he disown'd that unlimited Supremacy in Church-Affairs, which the Prelatists did afterwards grant to their Kings: and the Querists do here in plain Terms disown the Authority of both King and Parliament to restore those Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Ministers to their Right, from which they were in a tyrannical and illegal Manner ejected by the Council, and the Bishops and their Clergy obtruded upon the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Inclinations of the generality of the People, as has been asserted by Authority of the present Parliament; and without the Peoples Consent, Ministers can never be duly possessed of Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction. Christ makes his People a willing People in the Day of his Power, and does not impower his Ambassadors to exercise a Tyranny over them against their Wills: so that if any be refractory, and refuse to submit to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of the Church, they are to be esteem'd as Heathens and Publicans; and if the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists and their Adherents should continue obstinate, and refuse to come into the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som of the Church upon such-easy Terms of Conformity as are now enjoin'd, all that they do is but to declare themselves no Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the National Church, seeing they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to embrace either her Doctrine or Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. But by what Laws, Divine or Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, they and their said Adherents, who do not make up the tenth Part of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, should take upon them the Name of the National Church, they would do well to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the World.</p>
            <p>This leads me to another of the Reasons for their Protestation, <hi>viz.</hi> That they may
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199607:15"/>maintain the Liberties of that National Church.</p>
            <p>This is truly pleasant, that they should pretend to be the only Patriots for the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of the National Church, whom the Body of the Church in that Nation have voted to be the great and insupportable Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the same. This is just like the late King's Declarations, wherein he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a mighty Zeal for the Freedom and Liberties of the Nations which have by their Representatives dethron'd him for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to enslave them. But seeing these Gentlemen will not allow the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Assembly to be the true Representative of the National Church, because they have not Delegats from the Prelatical Curats and their Adherents, they would do well to show us the Deputations which they have from the Body of Protestants in the Nation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present them, and protest so strenuously for their Liberties. And seeing the Querists pretend so highly to maintain the Liberties of the National Church, we are willing that the World should judg whether they or the Presbyterians have maintained them best.</p>
            <p>The Presbyterians ever since the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation have pleaded, and often suffered for maintaining the Privilege of the Church to hold her own Courts, and be Judges of the Doctrine and Discipline of the Church. Whereas the Episcopalians have always sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the same to their Princes, how cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt soever either in Practice or Principle: and thus K. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d, though a dissolute vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, was <hi>impowered to emit and enact such Constitutions and Orders concerning Church-Administrations, Persons, Meetings and Matters, as he in his Wisdom should think fit, without so much as taking the Advice and Consent of his Parliament;</hi> and K. <hi>James</hi> the 7th, though a professed Papist, had the same Power: So that the National Church had no Privilege neither to will nor to do in any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Church-Constitutions, Administrations, Persons, Meetings,</hi> or <hi>Matters;</hi> for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, with their Clergy and Adherents, had made an absolute Surrender of them by that Act: whereas the Presbyterians, as Mr. <hi>Guthry</hi> above-mentioned, and others, chose rather to suffer Death, and to undergo a savage Persecution, than either consent or submit to such a manifest betraying of the Privileges of the National Church: and that the Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palians may be sensible what a horrid Piece of Treachery this Surrender of theirs was, let them peruse the following Declaration of their Head K. <hi>James</hi> VI. upon the Subject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matter; which he wrote with his own Hand, and signed and delivered it to the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> at <hi>Linlithgow, December</hi> 7. 1585.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I for my part shall never, neither my Posterity ought, ever cite, summon or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend any Pastor or Preacher for Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Doctrine in Religion, Salvation, Heresies, or true Interpretation of the Scripture: But according to my first Act, which confirmeth the Liberty of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word, Ministration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I avouch the same to be a Matter meer Ecclesiastical, and altogether imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to my Calling. Therefore never shall I, nor ever ought they, I mean my Posterity, acclaim any Power or Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in the foresaids. — And after: Christ saying <hi>Dic Ecclesiae,</hi> and one only Man stealing that Dint in a quiet Hole, the Act of Parliament reduceth the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for Informality and Nullity of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess; not as Judges whether the Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication was grounded on good and just Causes or not, but as Witnesses that it was unformally proceeded against the Warrant of God's Word, Example of all Reformed Kirks, and your own particular Custom in this Country. — And after: I acclaim not to my self to be Judg of Doctrine in Religion, Salvation, Heresies, or true Interpretation of Scripture. — And after: My Intention is not to meddle with Excommunication, neither acclaim I to my self, or my Heirs, Power in any thing that is meer Ecclesiastical, and not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nor with any thing that God's Word hath simply devolved in the Hands of his Kirk. And to conclude, I confess and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199607:16"/>Christ Jesus to be Head and Law-giver to the same. And whatsoever Persons do attribute to themselves as Head of the Kirk, and not as Members, to suspend or alter any thing that the Word of God hath only remitted to them, that Man I say committeth manifest Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now we see that this Learned Prince dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims any such Power to belong to himself or his Successors, as our Prelatists conierr'd upon his two Grandsons; and he absolutely declines being a Judg in Doctrine: and yet our Querists appeal to their present Majesties as the supreme Judges without any Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though they have been graciously plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to abolish that Act of Supremacy which did constitute them such; and as there's all the Reason of the World to believe, upon the very same Principle that K. <hi>James</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed it. But our Prelatists will have them to retain it whether they will or not, even against the Touch of their own Scepter; not out of any Good will to them, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest from the Carriage of the Party since the Revolution, but meerly to insinuate a malicious Reflection upon the Presbyterians, as if they did not allow their Majesties their full Power. Whatever Noise the Faction may make as if they propos'd these Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries meerly from Scruples of Conscience; the Presbyterians are not so ignorant of their Intrigues as they imagine, but know very well that the Hand of <hi>Joab</hi> is in the Affair, and by whom, and what Motives they are influenc'd and manag'd: and though the Point be too tender to be here insisted on, yet they may please to take notice of so much in plain Scots, that they have been disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in their Design of Rabbling, and now they betake themselves to revile the Committee and their Constituents.</p>
            <p>One thing more I cannot pass over, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Querists pretend that they don't decline the Committee's Authority with any Design to protect such as are truly guilty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, if there be any such; and yet Mr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Chrevey,</hi> the Clerk, or principal Man of their General Meeting, was judicially cited before the Committee, and did accordingly appear, and made several Answers in his Cause before them; which he ought not to have done if he had reckoned them an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Judicatory: And whether it does not look very suspicious, that he and the rest of the Querists were afraid of being found truly guilty, when though he had by his appearing and answering, own'd the Authority of the Judicatory; that yet he and they should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline it, and protest against it, before they proceeded to Sentence.</p>
            <p>— And what reason they have to decline the Authority of the Committee as Parties, will appear further from the Instructions gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Assembly to the Committee in 1690, with which those of the present Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee do without doubt run parallel, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>That none of them shall be removed, but such as are either Insufficient, Scandalous, Erroneous, or supinely Negligent; and that those of them be admitted to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterial Communion, who upon due Trial shall be found Orthodox, Able, Godly, Peaceable and Loyal; and that such who shall be found to have received Wrong in any inferiour Judicatory, should be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly redressed. — That they be very cautious of receiving Informations against the late Conformists, and that they proceed in the Matter of Censure very deliberately; so as none may have just Cause to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of their Rigidity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And that this Committee, against whom they cavil, have behaved themselves accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to these Instructions, appears from their receiving into Ministerial Communion at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdeen,</hi> the Persons named in the List, being such as were of the very best of their Party, and of good Esteem for their Learning and Piety: Whose Compliance does fret and enrage the factious Querists and others; who let them pretend what they will, endeavour to conceal Corruption both in Principle and Practice, under the Covert of their Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:199607:16"/>
            <head>Protestation of Mr. <hi>William Dunlop</hi> Principal of the College of <hi>Glasgow,</hi> against Mr. <hi>James Gordon</hi> and others.</head>
            <p>I <hi>Mr.</hi> William Dunlop <hi>Principal of the College of</hi> Glasgow, <hi>and one of the Members of the Committee of the last General Assemblie of this Church, Do protest and declare, That the Paper now given in by Mr.</hi> James Gordon <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent at</hi> Banchory, <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Crevey <hi>Incumbent at</hi> Newhills, <hi>and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their Brethren, may not be regarded, nor any way retard this Committee's Procedor in any of the Affairs committed to them, in respect that this Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee are clothed with their Power from the last General Assemblie: Which Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie was lawfullie indicted and held, and was a free and lawful General Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, conform to all the Laws and Rules of this Church and Nation, whether Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or Ecclesiastick; and against either the indicting or holding of which Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, or the Power and Authoritie thereof, none of these Appellants, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their pretended Perswasion, did make any publick Protest, or give in to the same, any Reasons against their Proceedings, or against the saids Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie's clothing this Committee with the Power given thereunto. And in respect the saids Mr.</hi> James Gordon, <hi>and others here present, do pretend to come as commissionat from a collective Body and Meeting of Ministers; which Body of Ministers have no Power and Authority by any of the Lawes and Rules of this Church and Kingdom to be such, nor have given these Proofs of their Loyalty to their Majesties of their owning and submitting to the Government of the Church now by Law established, as the Law doth require. And lykewayes in respect that these Appellants, except Mr.</hi> Thomas Crevey, <hi>doe come into this Judicatorie without being lawfullie called thereunto, and doe by their Appeal impugne the lawfull Authoritie of the same: And as to Mr.</hi> Crevey, <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect that he having been lawfullie cited to appear before this Judicatorie, to answer for several things laid to his Charge, hath sisted himself judiciallie before this Committee, and made several Answers</hi> in causa, <hi>and yet</hi> ante latam sententiam, <hi>hath given in this pretended Appeal. And lykewayes in respect that all these pretended Appellants give no Reasons for their Appeal, but put in Queries to this Committee, challenging the Authoritie of the same by Law established: In respect whereof, and for other Reasons which I shall humblie offer to this Committee when thereunto required, I do protest that the Committee may proceed to discuss the Lybel against Mr.</hi> Thomas Crevey, <hi>and perform all the other Trust reposed in them. And desiring that this my Declaration and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation may be recorded in the Registers of this Committee, there to remain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon I take Instruments, <hi>Sic Subscribitur,</hi> Will. Dunlop.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:199607:17"/>
            <p> AT <hi>Dundee</hi> Mr. <hi>John Chrystison</hi> Minister at <hi>Lyth,</hi> was received into Ministerial Comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and Mr. <hi>David Ogilvy</hi> at <hi>Aberbrothock</hi> was received as Probationer: Mr. <hi>Henry Scrimsor</hi> his Relation to <hi>Dundee</hi> was declared null by virtue of his Demission at the Session 5th <hi>November</hi> 90, from the Pulpit 11th <hi>November;</hi> and by a Letter to the Provost. Mr. <hi>George Graham</hi> Incumbent at <hi>Inneraritie</hi> was deposed for Drunkenness. <hi>Nota,</hi> He did not appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Committee, although he was in <hi>Dundee</hi> that Day; against which he was <hi>pro secundo</hi> cited, but on that same Day he was drunk in the Town, which particular Act was proven before the Committee besyde many other.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Affairs at <hi>Aberdeen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter all due legall and usuall Steps of Procedor had been observed;</p>
               <p>Yesterday being the 8th of <hi>July,</hi> the Elders and Deacons of the new Town of <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen</hi> were publicklie admitted, and this Day constitut themselves into a Session.</p>
               <p>Yesterday also one of the Charges was declared vacant, and Intimation made to all concerned in the Calling of a Minister, to meet together on Wednesday next.</p>
               <p>Yesterday lykewise the Church of the old Town (after the reading of Mr. <hi>Francis Ross</hi> his Sentence) was declared vacant, he discharged to preach any more there; and Intimation made to all Persons concerned, to give in Lists of Persons to be Elders and Deacons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A List of Persons received into Ministerial Communion at <hi>Aberdeen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>David Lindsay</hi> at <hi>Drumaik,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Anderson</hi> at <hi>Tarves,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Chalmer</hi> at <hi>Gartley,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Frazer</hi> at <hi>Stairs,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Thomson</hi> at <hi>Auchindore,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Johnston</hi> at <hi>Kern,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Garioch</hi> at <hi>Kennethmont:</hi> Who being all in the Synod of <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen,</hi> are to be erected in a Presbytrie on Wednesday next. Mr. <hi>Patrick Innes</hi> at <hi>Bamff</hi> in the Synod of <hi>Murray,</hi> is also received. Mr. <hi>John Auchterlonie</hi> at <hi>Fordoun</hi> hath applyed, but is delayed till the Committee return to <hi>Dundee,</hi> because he is in the Synod of <hi>Angus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A List of those whose Pastoral Relation to the respective Churches following, was declared null, they discharged to preach any more in them, because they had no Title or Right, but what a Call without the Interposition of the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of any Church-Judicatorie gave them; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Alexander Jamison</hi> and Mr. <hi>Andrew Dalgarnoe</hi> Competitors for <hi>Tyrie,</hi> Mr. <hi>Francis Rosse</hi> at old <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Forquhar</hi> at <hi>Ecclesgreig,</hi> Mr. <hi>Andrew Honyman</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationer at <hi>Kinness,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alexander Thomson</hi> at <hi>Terntric,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Turin</hi> at <hi>Inch,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Whyte</hi> at <hi>Strichen,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Chein</hi> at <hi>Raithen,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Houston</hi> at <hi>Lonmay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>William Mackay</hi> is transported from <hi>Dornoch</hi> to <hi>Cromdale.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199607:17"/>
            <head>The <hi>Representation</hi> of the Committee of the Assembly for the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the Privy-Council of that Kingdom.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>With some</hi> Queries, <hi>by another Hand, proposed to such Church-of</hi>-England-<hi>Men as are Advocates for the Scots Episcopalians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE publishing of the following <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation,</hi> &amp;c. so suddenly after the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the Scots Episcopal Queries and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation,</hi> may perhaps be look'd upon by some as an Effect of intemperate Heat: To such I shall only say, That the unwearied Endeavours of our Adversaries to misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest which they make amongst those of the highest Dignity of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to solicite their Majesties against the Scots Presbyterians, and lay such Misrepresenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before them as Matters of Truth, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it highly necessary to publish the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Paper, that the World may have a farther taste of the disingenuous Practices of the Scots Episcopalians, and that the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Men may them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves be Judges, Whether those of their Communion, who solicite their Majesties against the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> do not therein prefer their own peevish Humour to their Majesties Interest?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Lord High Chancellor, and remanent Lords of their Majesties Privy-Council of <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the General Assembly for the North,</head>
            <opener>Humbly sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THAT whereas the last General As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of this National Church, did grant Commission to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Number of Ministers and Elders for visiting the North, impowering them to purge and to plant Churches on the other side the River <hi>Tay;</hi> and to do and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in several other Matters, according to the Tenour of their Commission, which was drawn up and adjusted to the satisfaction of their Majesties Commissioner present in the Assembly in all Points. Conform where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we having made a Progress through the North; and in all our Actings, which were sincerely designed for the Advancement of the Gospel, the Quiet of the Church, for the promoting of their Majesties Interest, and the Publick Peace kept within Bounds prescribed to us. Yet the Refractoriness of several Persons justly censured by us, with some other Occurrents, wherein we conceived the Authority of their Majesties Laws and Government, as well as that of the Church, to be deeply concerned, do oblige us to lay before your Lordships the Particulars following.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199607:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>First;</hi> That notwithstanding several Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters have, after gross and uncontroverted Scandals objected and proven against them, been censured with Deposition, yet they presum'd to Preach, and exercise their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterial Function, in contempt of all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, both Civil and Ecclesiastick: Such as Mr. <hi>Geo. Graham,</hi> late Incumbent of <hi>Inne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarity,</hi> deposed for habitual Drunkenness, ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated with most scandalous Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Mr. <hi>John Lesly</hi> at <hi>Rothes,</hi> deposed for habitual Swearing, and horrid Cursings and Imprecations. Mr. <hi>James Smith</hi> at <hi>Killimore-Wester,</hi> for habitual Drunkenness; and Mr. <hi>George Seaton</hi> at <hi>Auchterlesse,</hi> for habitual Drunkenness, supine Negligence, and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious stirring up of Variance and Strife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Parishioners and Neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> That though upon exact trial, it was found that several Ministers and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers had intruded into Churches vacant, not only against good Order, but to the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of the regular planting of the said Churches, and therefore were discharged to preach any more there until orderly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, yet they continued to preach still, in contempt of the Sentences past against them; such as Mr. <hi>James Gordon</hi> Younger, at <hi>Foverane;</hi> and others: Which Contempt ought so much the more to be noticed by your Lordships, that now through the Care of this Commission, who have taken in thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Dissenting Ministers to the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Ministers formerly in those Bounds, Presbyteries are duly established within convenient Precincts; so as all the Churches vacant in these Parts may, upon an easy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, be regularly provided.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> That several Ministers deprived by your Lordships for their Disaffection, do nevertheless, contrary to your Lordships Sentence, and to the Act of Parliament 1690, whereby they are ordained first to qualify themselves in the Terms of the said Act, continue to preach in vacant and other Churches, in contempt of the said Act: Such as Mr. <hi>John Matters,</hi> late Incumbent at <hi>Ceres,</hi> intruding himself upon <hi>Elliot.</hi> Dr. <hi>John Nicholson,</hi> late at <hi>Errol;</hi> Mr. <hi>Will. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray,</hi> late at <hi>Cargill;</hi> Mr. <hi>David Anderson,</hi> late at <hi>Perth:</hi> All intruding upon <hi>Kilspindy,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming to preach there, and at other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly;</hi> Notwithstanding of the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of Prelacy, and the settling of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government in this Church, yet nevertheless Persons have received Orders from some of the late Bishops, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon usurped the Ministerial Function, and intruded into Churches: Such as Mr. <hi>John Auchterlonie</hi> in <hi>Aberlenno,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gideon Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thry</hi> Diaconat, in <hi>April</hi> last.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly;</hi> That notwithstanding our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission was legally given and authorised by the General Assembly of this National Church, established by Law, and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by their Majesties High Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; yet at <hi>Aberdeen</hi> twelve Ministers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one only was cited before us, took the boldness to give in a Paper, under the Title of <hi>Queries,</hi> plainly questioning, not only our Authority, but the Authority of the Law whereby the Government of this Church is settled: And though they got a very moderate and rational Answer, yet they protested against us, and appeal'd from the Commission, and that in the Name of the whole Ministers benorth <hi>Tay,</hi> though they shewed no Warrant from them. And further, they appeal'd to their Majesties Protection, albeit never so much as cited as said is, and that they themselves have not so much as taken the Oath of Allegiance to entitle them to this Protection. So that the Contrivance was evidently Factious, to stir up and animate all such as are disaffected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Government, both Civil and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastick. And thus at <hi>Innerness,</hi> four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen other Ministers did officiously give in a Paper of Adherence to the <hi>Aberdeen</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and made their Protest and Appeal in a ruder manner.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199607:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly;</hi> That when the Committee did summon Witnesses, particularly against Mr. <hi>Andrew Abercromby</hi> at <hi>Tarlen,</hi> a Person infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous through all that Country, by reason of his scandalous and flagitious Life, yet the Witnesses were kept back; which may be of bad Example, unless your Lordships prescribe some compulsory Method in time coming.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly;</hi> That notwithstanding that Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government is settled by Act of Parliament, and the Exercise thereof lodged in the Hands of the Ministers and Elders therein set down, yet many of the Episcopal Clergy in the North, do usurp Ecclesiastical Authority, and keep their own Meetings, where they license Preachers, order Admission of Ministers, supply Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancies, and do other Acts of Order and Discipline, contrary to the Law, and tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the establishment of a Schism in the Church, and to the visible Prejudice of their Majesties Interest.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly;</hi> That the Havers of Keys of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Vacant Churches, did refuse to make them forth-coming to the Committee; which was both against Law, and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships frequent Acts and Orders: And thus the Keys of the Kirks of <hi>Elliot</hi> and <hi>Kilspindie</hi> were refused by .... Havers thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly;</hi> That in all Churches where the Worship of God is performed, there ought to be no disorderly Interruption, upon any Pretence whatsoever: Yet in the Church of <hi>Old Aberdeen,</hi> several insolent Persons have presumed to interrupt the Worship of God, by offering at their own Hand another Piece of Worship most unseasonably, to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest profanation of the Publick Worship, and great disturbance of the Congregation, who gave no Compliance to the said Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order: Which being manifestly Factious, and in all probability fomented by Persons disaffected, doth not only occasion great Scandal, but is very like to grow to higher Degrees of Insolence if not timely restrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>And seeing that the happy Success that we have had, thrô the Blessing of God, in these Parts, by taking in and gaining a good Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ministers, and disposing others to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Example, and by recommending our Moderation to all the Well-affected in those Parts, and settling several Churches and Presbyteries, to the great Benefit of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, and the Advancement of their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Interest: Which doth in a manner wholly depend upon your Lordships inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing in the Premisses, and giving unto the Church and its Authority, that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and Assistance which the Law or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, and your Lordships know to be so necessary.</p>
            <p>May it therefore please your Lordships to take the Premisses into your serious Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, to apply such due Remedies to the above-mentioned Evils as the Law allows, and your Lordships shall find most proper, especially since we can confidently aver, that any Opposition or Discountenance we met with in those Parts, was only from Persons notoriously disaffected to their Majesties Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and principally upon that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and that where-ever Ministers, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the present Church-Government, are settled in the North, or have access to preach in those Bounds, there's a sensible growing of Affection among the People, to the Civil as well as to the Ecclesiastical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <closer>And your Lordships Petitioners shall ever pray.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199607:19"/>
            <head>Some <hi>Queries</hi> propounded to such Church-of<hi>-England-</hi>Men as are Advocates for the Scots Episcopal Clergy.</head>
            <p n="1">1. WHether the King and Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> have not as much Power to settle such a Government in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as is most sutable to the Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the People, as the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England</hi> have to settle such an one in the Church of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And if so, How it comes to pass that they offer to meddle in Affairs belonging to the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and solicite to have a Party still continued, not only in Benefices, but in the Exercise of Ecclesiastical Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, who refuse to qualify themselves according to Law?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether they would not highly resent it, if the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> should solicite for such things in favour of the Dissenters from the Church of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Seeing the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> does no such thing, whether Scots Men have not just Cause to suspect that those English Men who are so bold as to interpose in Affairs that are already determined by the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Scotland,</hi> have a mind to revive the old Pretensions of our Crown's being held in Fee of theirs, and that our Church ought to be subject to theirs?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether or not, seeing that Matter hath been determined long ago by the Point of the Sword, Prescription of Time, and the Union of the Crowns, the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> may not expect as much Justice from the King and Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> against such Incendiaries, if they should make Application for it now, as they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd against others of the like sort, both in Church and State, within the Memory of Man?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether the moderate Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Men have not reason to suspect that Part of the Plot reaches them, seeing they were also persecuted under the Notion of <hi>Whigs</hi> and <hi>Trimmers</hi> in the late Reigns, when the Scots Presbyterians were under the Hatches, especially seeing the Scots Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palians are generally in the late King's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> some of their greatest Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> have lately writ to the King, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, to their false Representation of Affa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> those who endeavoured to have such Men only in Places of Power and Trust, as concurr'd in the Murder of my Lord <hi>Russel,</hi> and such other worthy Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Men in the late Reigns?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether it's possible that they can be so far impos'd upon, as to think that the Scots Episcopalians decline Conformity to Presbyterian Government in Point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; when it appears by Parl. 2. Act 1. <hi>Car.</hi> II. that it was the Opinion of the Party then, that the ordering of the Government of the Church did properly belong to his Majesty and Successors; and that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives of the Party did offer to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to, and concur with Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by their <hi>Formula</hi> in 1690, if their signing of the <hi>Confession of Faith</hi> could have been dispens'd with?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether the Scots Episcopalians be not guilty of very gross Dissimulation, in pretending a Deference to the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they act so contemptuously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Acts of Parliament and Council in so many things, as appears by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee's <hi>Representation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being judged sufficient at present, those who desire a farther Account of the Party, are referred to the Answer to the <hi>Scots Presbyterian Eloquence,</hi> the Continuation of it, the <hi>Scots Episcopal Innocence,</hi> and the <hi>Reflections on their Queries and Protestation,</hi> all sold by the Booksellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>